ARGHYA CHATTERJEE



50, BC Das Lane, Lalbagh, Dhaka, BD



+88-01943753798

arghyame20buet@gmail.com

https://arghyachatterjee.github.io

A machine learning researcher expert in applying deep learning & cloud computing in computer vision, data-driven modern astronomy and practical robotics & systems engineering application in order to serve the society & in greater sense the world, and encourage collaborative endeavor to explore outer world for better future of mankind.

EDUCATION

Bangladesh University of Engineering and Technology, Dhaka, Bangladesh

Degree: BSc. in Mechanical Engineering

Feb 2015 - Sept 2019

CGPA: 3.14/4.00

Khulna Public College, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: HSC in Science GPA: 5.00/5.00

Jul 2012 - Aug 2014 Class Position: 1st/60

Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School, Khulna, Bangladesh

Degree: SSC in Science GPA: 5.00/5.00

Jan 2010 - May 2012

Class Position: 1st/60

RESEARCH & PROJECT EXPERIENCE

Graduate Research Assistant & Software Team Advisor

Model & Project Lab, Int. Mars Rover Competition (URC & ERC) Sep 2019 – Present Supervisors: Dr. Md. Ashigur Rahman and Mizanul H. Chowdhury Dhaka, Bangladesh Topic: Autonomous Navigation Based on GPS, SLAM, AR Tag and Object Detection for Safe Exploration of Rovers on Rough Terrains, Caves and Mineral Ores of Earth and Mars.

Researcher & Collaborator

Undergraduate Thesis

Mar 2018 - Apr 2019

Supervisors: Dr. Maglub Al Nur and Dr. Muhammad Abir

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Computational Investigation on Pool Boiling IR Images for Segmentation of Dry Spots Automatically and Evaluating Performance of Traditional Image Processing and Deep Neural Networks in Quantifying Dry Area Segments.

Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project

Mar 2017 - Feb 2018

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Musanna Galib

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Fire and Flood Fighter Octocopter (UAV) for Extinguishing Fire in Fire Affected Buildings and Areas, and Distributing Flood Reliefs to people in Flood Affected Zones.

Researcher & Technical Lead

Microsoft BD Internship Project

Feb 2017 - May 2017

Supervisors: Sonia B. Kabir and Ashikur Rahman

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Earlier Screening of Particular Disability in Children Through Mobile Application Using Microsoft Products like Azure Cloud Platform and Bing Maps Server.

Researcher & Team Leader

Undergraduate Project

Jul 2016 - Feb 2017

Supervisors: Dr. M.A. Rashid Sarkar and Dr. A. B. M. Alim Al Islam

Dhaka, Bangladesh

Topic: Hand Wearable Solar Powered Obstacle Detection and Safe Navigation Device for

Blind People in Low Cost.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

• BUET Mars Rover Robotics Team Instructor at Model & Project Lab, BUET

• National Space Carnival & Camp Instructor & Academic Coordinator for Workshops & Camps

• Bangladesh Astronomical Society Instructor for Workshops & Seminars Sep 2019 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Jun 2019 - Present Dhaka, Bangladesh Jan 2016 - May 2019 Dhaka, Bangladesh

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

• Youthprenuer Network (A Social Welfare Organization) Jun 2019 – Present Head of STEM Education & Development Dhaka, Bangladesh Activities: Instructed, Organized and Lead Projects, Workshops, Olympiads and Camps in Educational Institutions to Promote STEM Education Specially among Children and Women of Bangladesh.

• American Astronomical Society

Country Co-Ordinator & Member

Activities: Celebrated International Astronomical Events in Bangladesh in accordance with AAS, and Reported to Proper Authority for Publishing on their Monthly Magazines.

• Bangladesh Astronomical Society
Organizer & Member
Activities: Instructed and Organized Workshops, Quizzes and Seminars on Space and Astronomy to Promote Space Education among Future Generation of Bangladesh.

PUBLICATIONS

- **A. Chatterjee**, M. Galib and M. A. R. Sarkar, "Application of Arduino in designing modern electromechanical laboratory," *2017 IEEE International Conference on Power, Control, Signals and Instrumentation Engineering (ICPCSI)*, Chennai, 2017, pp. 222-225.
- **A. Chatterjee**, S. Dutta, P. Sarkar and A. B. M. A. A. Islam, "Obstacle Detector for Blind People with Low Cost (Poster Presentation)," *Proceedings of 2017 International Conference on Networking, Systems and Security (NSysS)*, Dhaka, 2017.

INTERNSHIPS & TRAININGS

Microsoft Bangladesh
 Internship Project: Disabling Disability through Microsoft Products

 Khulna Power Company Limited
 Training: Power Plant Visit & Industrial Attachment (3 weeks)

 Feb 2017 - May 2017
 Dhaka, Bangladesh
 Oct 2018 - Oct 2018
 Khulna, Bangladesh

SKILL SETS

- **Prg. Language:** Python, C++, C#, C, Arduino, JavaScript, HTML, PHP, CSS, SQL & LATeX.
- **Framework & OS:** ROS, Nvidia Isaac Sdk, Keras, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Kubernetes, .NET, Django, WordPress, Linux, Mac & Windows.
- **Software & Tool:** Git & GitHub, Bash, Docker, MySQL, MIPAR, SOLIDWORKS, AutoCAD, Ansys, Eagle, PLC, Blender3D, Unity & Unreal Engine 4 & Microsoft Office Family.
- **IDE, Compiler & Text Editor:** CodeBlocks, Microsoft Visual Studio, MATLAB, Node.js, Atom, Jupiter Notebook, PyCharm, Spyder, Visual Studio Code, Notepad++ & Sublime Text.

- Cloud Platform: AWS Compute, RoboMaker & Storage, Google Cloud Platform & Colab & Microsoft Azure Cloud Platform.
- **Hardware:** GPS, LIDAR, 3D Stereo Camera, Nvidia Jetson ARM Boards, Raspberry PI, Arduino Series & Nvidia AMD Boards with GTX & RTX Graphics.
- **Technology:** Computer Vision, SLAM & Path Planning, PCB Design, 3D Printing, AR & VR, Game Development, Web Development, GPU & Cloud Computing & Data Science.
- **Language:** Bangla, English & Hindi.
- Others: Astronomy, Creative Arts, Singing, Harmonium & Guitar Playing, Organizing, Show Hosting, Volunteering, Swimming, Cycling, Playing Cricket, Football & Badminton.

AWARDS, HONORS & SCHOLARSHIPS

• 2nd in Asia and 16th across the Globe in European Rover Challenge	Sep 2019
European Space Foundation (ESF) & European Space Agency (ESA)	Kielce, PL
Hon. Mention in National Project Show Competition	Jul 2017
IEEE SS12 & Maker Fair, UIU	Dhaka, BD
• 1st in National Project Show Competition	Jun 2017
EEE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 3rd in Inter University Project Show Competition	May 2017
Mechanical Festival, BUET	Dhaka, BD
• 1st in National Poster Presentation Competition	Mar 2017
Robolution, MIST	Dhaka, BD
• 2nd in Inter University Project Show Competition	Dec 2016
CSE Day, BUET	Dhaka, BD
 Gold, Bronze & Silver Recipient of Duke of Edinburgh Int. Award 	Dec 2019
Duke of Edinburgh International Award Association	London, UK
• 1st in All Classes in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2002-2014
Elizabeth Primary Sc., Khulna BKS Sc., Khulna Pub. Cl.	Khulna, BD
• Govt. Board Scholarship in Primary, Junior, Secondary & H. Secondary	2006-2014
Education Board of Bangladesh Govt., Jessore	Khulna, BD
Olympiad Achievements:	
• 1st in Reg. R. of Science Olympiad'14 • 1st in Reg. R. of Zoology	Olympiad'14
• 3 rd in Reg. & 10 th in Nat. R. of Astro-Olympiad'13 • 3 rd in Reg. R. of Math Ol	lympiad'14

CERTIFICATIONS

- Intro to Satellite Communications by Institut Mines Télécom on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **Wireless Communications for Everybody** by Yonsei University on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **AstroTech:** The Science and Technology behind Astronomical Discovery by The University of Edinburgh on Coursera, Dec 2019.
- **Image and Video Processing:** From Mars to Hollywood with a Stop at the Hospital by Duke University on Coursera, Oct 2019.
- **Deep Learning Specialization** (5 Course) by Deeplearning.ai on Coursera, Sept 2018.
- A Short Course on **Nuclear Power Engineering** by Institute of Nuclear Power Engineering, BUET, Apr 2018.

LEADERSHIPS

•	Head of STEM Education & Development	Youthprenuer Network
•	Software Team Lead	Team Interplanetar, BUET
•	Technical Lead of Internship Project	Microsoft BD
•	President (Senior Rover Mate)	BUET Rover Scout Group

President

- Team Lead for Development & Planning
- Founding Member
- Country Co-Ordinator
- **Organizing** Secretary

Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET
ESAB, BUET Unit
Sceptre
American Astronomical Society
Nuclear Engineering Club, BUET

VOLUNTEERING

• Sceptre (Poverty Alleviation Organization)

Activities: Org. free medical camps & distribute dress & sewing machines to poor people.

BUET Rover Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on annual sports day, alumni day & admission test day at BUET.

Khulna Bidyut Kendra Secondary School Scout Group

Activities: Volunteered on medical camps, tree plantation events & sports day at KBKSS.

WORKSHOPS & SEMINARS

- National Leadership Conference-2019 arranged by WOC and English Olympiad.
- Youth Leadership Summit-2016 organized by Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre.
- 4th BIRDS International Workshop on **Demystifying Satellites** org. by BRAC University.
- **Seminar on "Zero Robotics"** organized by Dept. of Mechanical Engineering, BUET.
- Introducing Bangladesh Model World Health Organization & Workshop on WHO Simulation organized by BMWHO & UNYSAB.
- Authorship Workshop on **How to Publish a Technical Paper with IEEE** org. by IEEE.
- Training on **AI for Beginners** organized by Satyen Bose Science Club, BUET.
- Workshops on **CFD**, **Ansys Fluent**, **Solidworks & 3D Printing** org. by Involute Tech BD.
- Workshops on **PCB & Graphic Designing** organized by IEEE, BUET & BD Section.
- Workshop on Overall Understanding of Scouting org. by BUET Rover Scout Group.

MEMBERSHIPS

- Institute of Electrical and Electronics Engineers (IEEE)
- American Society of Mechanical Engineers (ASME)
- American Astronomical Society (AAS)
- American Physical Society (APS)
- American Nuclear Society (ANS)
- Bangladesh Astronomical Society (BAS)
- Bangladesh Youth Leadership Centre Graduate Network (BGN)
- Engineering Students Association of Bangladesh (ESAB)

REFERENCES

Dr. M. A. Rashid Sarkar

Academic Advisor Ex. Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Professor, Dept. of Nuclear Eng., MIST.

Dr. Maglub Al Nur

Thesis Supervisor Professor, Dept. of Mech. Eng., BUET. Dr. Muhammad Abir

Thesis Co-Supervisor Ex. Post Doc. R. Associate, Dept. of NSE, MIT. Imaging Specialist, Phoenix Nuclear Labs.

Mizanul H. Chowdhury

Project Co-Supervisor Arch. & Admin of ZR, Space Sys. Labs, MIT.